welcome to what could be the first video
in a series of functional programming
that i've been wanting to make for a
long long time i believe that all
developers should learn functional
programming functional programming is a
style of writing code now this means
that if you learn functional programming
if you like those ideas you are going to
be able to apply them with whatever
language you like to work with now of
course there are programming languages
like clojure or scala that are more
designed for functional programming and
that have many built-in features that
make it easier for us to write
functional code but nevertheless
learning functional programming is a
skill that will help you no matter what
language you write on
learning functional programming will
give you a new perspective and approach
when solving programming problems
functional programming is not something
that you can learn and internalize in
one afternoon functional programming is
like a mindset it's a different way of
thinking and structuring your code
learning it is going to make you a
better developer now this might be my
personal opinion but i feel like when i
write functional code the code is
cleaner right from the start and it's
harder for me to make bugs happen in the
code box cannot hide so easy when you
write your code in a functional style
and last but not least functional
developers are some of the best paid
professionals in our industry the top
four highest paid programming languages
are all functional programming languages
i don't think that this means that if we
learn functional programming we're just
going to get immediately a salary raise
what i think this means is that
experienced developers senior developers
with really good cvs and very good
skills ended up gravitating and choosing
functional programming languages as they
progress in their careers now having
said all these good things about
functional programming i have to say
that i didn't have an easy time
understanding functional programming it
didn't really click in my brain as easy
as other things click and that's not
because the rules of functional
programming or the concepts are hard to
understand or memorize instead i think
it's because the explanations that i
have seen about functional programming
focus too much on the definitions of the
terms like immutability pure functions
side effects all those things they
define the terms very well but they fail
to show the developers why is a good
thing to write your code functionally
it's hard to sell functional programming
to developers it's hard to see the
benefit of functional programming if
instead of writing code and experience
functional programming we focus on the
definitions and the history and all
those things so what i would like to do
in this video maybe in this series if
you like this video you know if i can
make more videos about functional
programming what i would like to do
would be to experience functional
programming by comparing pieces of code
written in different styles of
programming to see what the benefits are
how they are different and which one we
like the most so to see how some
concepts of functional programming can
make our code better right from the
start today we're going to talk about a
concept called imperative code versus
declarative code when you write
declarative code your code is written to
express the outcome that you want when
you write imperative code your code is
written as a step-by-step instruction to
the computer to arrive to the outcome
that you want
before we freak out let's look at a
language that is declarative and that
many of us have used already whether we
knew it was declarative or not that
language is css css is a declarative
language because as you can see here in
this code if i want to change the
background color of the body all i have
to do is write down the outcome that i
want
as you can see i'm not writing down the
step-by-step instructions to the
computer to turn the background color
into tomato
i just tell the browser what i want and
the browser will figure out how to do it
i don't have to write the code to get
the body element and check if it exists
and then enter the styles and then
override the background color i don't
have to do any of those things if i did
those things if i wrote those steps down
that will be imperative code
remember
declarative is about expressing what
outcome you want an imperative is about
expressing how to get to that outcome
step by step so let's now solve a couple
of code challenges in an imperative way
in a declarative way and then we can see
which way we like the most the code will
be in javascript which is an imperative
programming language but it has many
methods and many functions that allow us
to apply declarative style to our code
now if you don't know javascript then
the examples are maybe not going to make
a lot of sense and if you want to learn
javascript for free then please click
the link below because they are going to
find a course do their javascript for
free with me but if you already know
javascript but you want to learn things
like react.js react native redox next js
next js apollo go python among many
other things you can also learn them for
free in the link below with me so our
first code challenge is very easy all i
want to do is i want to make a function
that receives a string and removes all
the spaces from that string and replaces
them with hard emojis now the imperative
way of solving this problem would be
something like this
all we are doing here is creating a
variable to hold the final result
then we look inside of each character of
the text that we want to clean
and depending if the character is a
space or not
we add a heart or the character to the
resulting string and when we are done we
return the result
as you can see this code is very very
imperative we are writing one by one all
the steps that need to be taken to
fulfill the requirements of this
function now let's look at the same
function but this time let's use
declarative programming
here we are using a method that all
strings have in javascript called
replace all where the first argument is
the text i want to replace and the
second one is the text i want to replace
it with it has the same result as the
imperative function and also is easier
to read and know what the function is
doing now maybe in the background in the
inside of the replace all function there
is maybe some imperative code like the
one that we wrote before this is why you
could say that all declarative code is
built on top of imperative code but as
developers don't have to write
imperative code instead we can use
functions that allow us to avoid writing
imperative code apart from the code
being longer in the imperative function
there is also a problem that arises from
being able to implement the solution
however we want to if we just write
imperative code we might make a mistake
and introduce a bug for example and our
teammates when they are reading our
imperative code will have a hard time
understanding what we are trying to do
at first glance they will have to read
step by step all the imperative code
that we wrote to be able to understand
what the function is doing in our last
code challenge let's now make a function
that removes all the odd numbers from an
array of numbers the imperative version
looks something like this which as you
can see is sort of similar to what we
did before but the declarative version
uses the filter function and it looks
something like this the first argument
of the filter method is a function which
is something very common in functional
programming languages where you are
going to be sending functions as
arguments and also you can receive
functions as values the filter function
will return an array with all the
elements that pass a condition the
condition is expressed in the function
that is on the first argument
that function will be called for each
item inside of the items array
if that function returns true then the
item will be added to the resulting
array if it returns false it will go
bye-bye
as you can see here we're just
specifying what is the filter that we
would like to apply to the array we are
not concerned with how this filter will
be applied let me know in the comments
which approach do you like the most do
you like imperative or declarative i
personally like declarative more i try
to use declarative code and functions as
much as i can but of course it's always
important to use the right tool for the
job some people dislike the declarative
style because they say that to be able
to understand that declarative code you
have to know what is the replace all
function you have to know what is the
filter function in advance and that's it
for today's video i just wanted to give
you a tiny taste into how functional
programming concepts help you approach
problem solving in a different way how
they help you think about the way you
write code in a different way as you saw
the two styles couldn't be more
different and one of them is more
elegant in a way than the other there
are more functional programming concepts
to discover but i'm not sure if my
audience would like me to keep talking
about functional programming so if you
do if you would like me to make more
videos about fb then please let me know
in the comments thank you so much for
watching as always stay happy stay free
stay healthy eat kimchi kamzamita salan
hayo see you on the next one bye